NICOLAS MITCHELL

nicomitchell502@gmail.com https://nico-mitchell.com

About Me

Nicolas Mitchell is a software engineer who focuses on networking, automation, dev-ops, and distributed system design. When he's not working, he can be found in the climbing gym, playing video games, and contributing to opensource projects. Nico speaks English, Spanish, and Portuguese.

Skills

Areas of Expertise: Backend development, cloud infrastructure, networking, containers, concurrency, distributed systems, automation Programming and Scripting Languages: C, JavaScript, Go, C++, Bash, Java, Python, Rust Other Technologies: AWS, Docker, Ansible, Linux, SQL Databases, NOSQL Databases, React, Git, Kubernetes, Splunk

Open-Source Contributions

Godot Engine Zellij

Hackathons

FirstBuild Hack the Home 2017, 2018 VandyHacks 2017 DerbyHacks

Hobbies and Talents

Spoken Languages: English (fluent), Spanish (fluent), Portuguese (intermediate) Music: Guitar (12 years), Singing (in a band), production (making beats with friends) Fitness: Indoor rock climbing (bouldering), weightlifting

Education

SAP

Bachelor of Science – Computer Science and Engineering May 2020 University of Louisville – JB Speed School of Engineering **GPA**: 3.341/4.0

Work Experience

Software Engineer – Observability

September 2020 – Present Palo Alto, CA

Reduced the need for manual task execution by working on a team to architect and build an automated workflow scheduler

- Improved automated processes for server deployment and setup scripts
- Created visibility into critical production systems by building Splunk dashboards
- Ensured production deployment processes could be verified by writing deployment
- Simplified deployment by automating container building, pushing, and running using Ansible

Software Engineering Intern – Data Platform Red Ventures

June 2019 – August 2019 Fort Mill. SC

- Developed backend micro-services in Golang for an internal data pipeline software
- Facilitated new software features by writing SQL database migrations
- Allowed for data connections between third party data providers like Segment and internal data pipeline by building Golang plugins
- Improved UX and integrated new backend components to web frontend with ReactJS

Visiting Research Assistant

January 2019 - May 2019

University of Southern California – Information Sciences Institute Researched and developed a system component for a DARPA funded project to

Waltham, MA

- automatically detect and respond to phishing emails
- Developed new features and fixed bugs for a Python natural language processing framework

Software Developer Intern

January 2018 - April 2018

El Toro

Louisville, KY

- Wrote an internal REST API with Golang to process, and schedule tasks using AWS
- Facilitated integrations for various databases including MongoDB, Aerospike, and PostgreSQL by creating and implementing a common interface
- Sped up internal data ingestion tool by over 1000% by implementing concurrent line processing using a worker pool
- Improved test coverage to 100% by adding necessary unit and integration tests in Golang

Student Tutor

August 2017 – April 2020

University of Louisville Resources for Academic Achievement

Louisville, KY

Tutored students in Python, C, C++, Data Structures and Algorithms, and other CS topics

Applied Experience

Embedded Systems: Interfaced and displayed vehicle ECU data with an Arduino and LED screen, built a self-orienting solar panel using an Atmel microcontroller, built a touchsensor game on a Raspberry Pi.

IoT/Serverless: Designed, developed, and deployed an IoT pilot project that ran sensor data through AWS IoT to an Aurora Serverless database cluster using a lambda function. Networking/Architecture: Managed microservices in an AWS VPC separated into public and private subnets. Included components were a database, web API, and web client. Integrated web API and client with Auth0 SSO.

Distributed Systems: Developed networked chat room in Golang using a custom TCP protocol, deployed on AWS Elastic Containers. Developed naïve implementation of a gossip protocol deployed on a network of docker containers.